okay okay today we're gonna talk about
Markov decision processes which are
generalization of search problems where
you're not entirely sure what your
actions are gonna do until you try them
so why would we consider a kind of
non-deterministic search right we had
our search problems before they had
States they had actions they had costs
and we made plans we liked perhaps to be
moving a robot around a grid to
accomplish some task or a pacman around
a board the reason why we need to have a
non-deterministic search is because in
the real world often you know what
actions are available to you and you
know what they might do but you're not
entirely sure what outcome will occur so
for example if you're this robot here
trying to cross this ledge you know you
can shimmy to the side and try to get
that gem and it might work or you might
fall into the pit and so when you take
an action you may know the possible
outcomes but you don't know which one is
going to happen and so you have to make
plans or more generally compute policies
that take into account all of the
different outcomes that might occur in
response to your actions
one example of not knowing what's gonna
happen is when you hit the spacebar
usually you get the next slide but
sometimes it all freezes up
luckily my policy knows what to do when
that happens so we're gonna have a
couple running examples just like when
we talked about search we had running
examples of search so we talked about
the specific examples of search or csps
or games and then we talked about a
whole class of search problems or csps
or or games the running example we're
gonna use for mdps markov decision
processes is grid world but just like in
all those other cases it's just a
running example so in grid world we have
a maze we have a robot we have north
south east and west and we're gonna have
a bunch of grid world concepts which are
really good for illustrating the kinds
of things that happen in MVPs but we're
gonna have to be really careful that we
don't over fit it's a flash-forward to
the machine learning section at the end
we don't want to over fit to this
particular example so in grid world
which is just one of a whole rich world
of possible MVPs we have a problem that
looks a little bit like a maze the agent
is going to be on a grid and they're
gonna be walls blocking the agents path
I love it when they install stuff for me
let's go get rid of you ok they're gonna
be walls blocking agents paths this is a
lot like moving pac-man around a maze
except now there's gonna be some
non-determinism and in this case in this
particular MDP that that non-determinism
is going to take take the shape of noise
so in this grid world say 80% of the
time when you take an action which might
be called north you'll actually move to
the north remember and search you would
just decide where you want to go and
then you'd be there but here you try to
move north but it might fail so in grid
world your actions might succeed and
that means you're going to move in the
direction you attempted to move or they
might fail which means something else
happens and in this formulation of grid
world and we could formulate grid world
a million different ways formulating a
problem so that it matches the brought
the real world problem you're trying to
solve
is one of the challenges in using these
techniques but in this grid world 80% of
time you go where you expected if
there's no wall there if there's a wall
there you'll just bounce off and stay
put the other 20% of the time you either
go counterclockwise or clockwise a
direction so 10% of the time if you go
to try to go north you'll actually go
west 10% of the time if you try to go
north you'll actually go east in this
grid world you're totally safe from
going south that's something that will
never happen in this model if you try to
go north this is how the real robots
work not really this is how the grid
world we're going to use for this
lecture and the next one works if
there's a wall in the direction you
would have gone you stay put all right
that's sort of the rules about where you
can move you can move north south east
west but it might fail sending you in an
unexpected direction now let's talk
about the equivalent of costs from
search an MDP is the costs are called
rewards and here we receive two kinds of
rewards they're sort of the primary grid
world reward which is that you exit the
game and there's kind of good exits and
bad exits and they're labeled with a
value so in this case the gem might be
the good exit if you can get to that
square you take the action exit it ends
the game you get your plus-one reward
and you're a happy robot if you fall
into the pit you also take the action
exit you receive your -1 reward the game
still ends except now you're a sad robot
those are the big rewards they can be
good or bad positive or negative and in
grid world to illustrate some concepts
we sometimes also have a living reward
which happens every step that you don't
exit the game so for example in this
position here I might decide to take the
action north maybe it succeeds and I
actually moved to to the square to the
north of the current robot and I get a
little reward it could be a tiny little
tiny little boost a positive reward or
it could be a tiny little bit of pain or
something like that as a negative reward
or it could be big or it could be zero
that's something we can change and
that's something that you get every step
of the game this notion of a living
reward and a big reward at the end and a
gem and a firepit these are all grid
world concepts but the idea that when
you take a transition from a state to
another state you receive a reward of
some
kind that's an MDP notion the goal
loosely because we're going to revisit
this later in this lecture the goal
loosely is to maximize the sum of the
rewards okay so you would like to take
actions so that you get the gem but you
don't fall into the pit okay that's a
little lot like search right when we
were trying to take actions which in
that case minimize cost now we're trying
to maximize rewards in a deterministic
grid world we could have solved the
problem with search we could have said
all right I'm in this state here and
what can I do well I can move north I
can move west North is a good move west
is a bad move so I'll move north and
when I choose that action I know what's
gonna happen
there is one outcome per action that's
what it means to say you have a
deterministic search problem in a Markov
decision problem
it's non-deterministic which means when
I'm in a certain state like the robots
right there to the right of the pit and
I choose to move north there's multiple
things that could happen okay
importantly in an MDP I know the set of
possible outcomes and it's actually
gonna turn out I know the probability
that each one will occur I just don't
know which one will occur in a given run
so when I plan to go north here I know I
might go north or I might go to the east
and have to replan from there or I might
go to the west and fall into the pit and
that'll be bad and as I plan I need to
take these things into account so I
might take for example a cautious sort
of behavior that takes into account all
of the possible failures along the way
so in general an MDP a Markov decision
process will be defined much in the way
a search problem was by a set of
quantities that define the problem
there's a set of states this is very
much like in search these are the set of
configurations of your problem there's a
set of actions and we had these in
search two sometimes we didn't really
talk about the actions having labels
when we talked about say depth-first
search but there were neighbors there
was a successor function and in your
code in project one you did actually
have to manage the labels of the action
so this is something that's been there
all along their states and their actions
the difference is that in search when
you're in a state and you take an action
there is a successor state and a cost in
an MDP there's not just one successor
state there are multiple so we've got
our state's like before we've got our
actions like before but now if I'm in
state s and I choose action a there may
be multiple states s Prime that can
occur as a result and so what I will
have is what's called a transition
function which describes from state s
and action a what s Prime's can happen
and with what probability so people
write t si s Prime and call it a
transition function but what you should
have in your head is this is for being
in state s choosing action a and what I
care about is the probability that every
possible outcome s Prime happens so T si
s prime is in this sense a conditional
probability that s prime will happen if
you were in state a state s and chose
action a another important quantity in
an MDP is a reward function so a reward
function in general is going to be a
positive or negative or zero reward that
you get if you're in state s you choose
action a and you land in state s prime
sometimes it'll only depend on s
sometimes it will only depend on s prime
sometimes it'll depend on the entire
triple that triple is often called a
transition and in general will write the
reward function as being a function of
where you started what you did and where
you landed so if you're standing next to
the if you're on the cliff trying to
cross the cliff there might be one
reward for making it across and an
entirely different reward if you fall
into the fire pit general there's may be
a start state there might be a terminal
state this is where things start to
differ in search there was this really
important notion of a goal a goal test
these are the states where where we stop
we've achieved our goal in mdps
in full generality the game sort of just
keeps playing and sometimes you get into
a state where it stops
sometimes the games go on forever and
we'll need to be very careful with our
algorithms and our formulations that we
understand what that
that a game may go on forever so MDP is
like I said are a class of
non-deterministic search problems and
they will require a new class of
algorithms to solve them so a-star
search won't do it that's for
deterministic search problems so how are
we gonna solve NDP's we're gonna talk
about a bunch of algorithms today and
next class and then in some sense the
week after that as well because it turns
out that MVPs are the foundation for
reinforcement learning as well however
you actually already have an algorithm
for solving MVPs
it's called expect a max search when you
learned about expect a max search it
might have felt like a weird variant of
minim acts where the opponent was
rolling dice or something like that but
it's actually the more general algorithm
and here we'll see that it's very
tightly related to the algorithms we
used to solve MVPs
okay so MVPs are like search problems
but instead of knowing what your action
will do you have a distribution over
possible outcomes represented by the
transition function okay any questions
all right so is this Markov guy and
what's he doing in my decision problem
Markov in AI usually means something
about the present state and it means
that given the present state the future
in the past are independent in an
appropriate sense and in a Markov
decision process what markov means is
that the action outcomes so those
transition probabilities of what will
happen if I take this action in this
state they can depend on the state and
they can depend on the action but they
can't depend on the past so if I want to
know I'm the robot and I want to know
what's gonna happen if I defy it across
this bridge well it depends on where I
am and what I'm doing but it doesn't
depend on the route that I took to get
there so if you'll remember this is just
like what we had in search we had to be
very careful to formulate our search
problem so the state had any information
stuffed into it that was necessary to
let the successor function fully
describe the problem and so with search
we often formulated all right okay my
state can't just be pac-man's position
it's also got to be which dots I've
eaten or where the walls still are or
whatever is appropriate for that
variation MVPs are the same way we often
have to be careful how we formulate our
states
so they give us this Markov property
that if I know the state and I know the
action I can tell you the distribution
over what happens next in a way that's
independent of what's happened in the
past okay thank you Markov here's
another big difference from search in
search we have this model of the agent
that looked at the search problem and
did a bunch of offline computation
thought and thought and thought and came
up with a plan what's a plan a plan is a
sequence of actions and then we would
execute that plan step by step and as we
execute that plan our master design
would fall into place action by action
and we'd end up at the goal state
exactly the way we planned MVPs are for
a noisier world and so we can't really
have a plan because it might work or it
might not
so let me give you an example I'm gonna
pull up grid world here
all right here is grid world on the
right and here on the left you're gonna
see well you can't really tell what I'm
pressing so you'll be able to see what
happens for each transition as I press
so here the robot is the blue dot and
you can see one that's the good exit
with the gem minus one is the bad exit
with the firepit and I'm gonna press
north south east or west and the robot
may or may not go the direction I cross
so what direction should we go let's try
north I'm gonna press the up key on my
keyboard what will happen who knows okay
so it worked all that all that suspense
this said started in state zero zero
took action north ended in state zero
comma one that is a transition asked was
zero zero a was North s prime was zero
one and I got a little reward my reward
was negative 0.1 does in this particular
configuration of of grid world you get a
minus 0.1 each time and that might
affect your behavior so as we change
their living reward up and down we'll
get different grid worlds in which the
optimal actions are gonna be different
behaviors we'll see that in a second so
I'm gonna try to go north again I'm
gonna press North again okay it works so
far it's acting pretty deterministic so
we started in state zero one we took
action north and we ended in state zero
two we might not have we might have
ended somewhere else but that's what
happened this time that's a transition
SAS Prime and we got an instantaneous
reward minus 0.1 so far my rewards are
minus point two okay I'm gonna try to go
east it worked
to something random okay um I went east
and it worked I'm gonna try to go east
again oh look at this started in state
one two I took action in East and I
ended in state one two that wasn't the
most likely outcome but that's what
happened here and so when I plan I need
to plan knowing that these things might
not go the way I expected so if I had
just blindly executed up up East East
East East exit
I'd be in trouble because it didn't
something didn't go sort of according to
plan something didn't have its most
likely outcome here
I'm gonna go east again though because
that's still a good idea whenever
that state that's a good idea okay no
I'm gonna go east again now here it
starts to get a little bit a little bit
suspenseful because I could successfully
go into the good exit or I could move
perilously close to the fire pit let's
try it east lucky okay and then from
this point you'll notice I received only
that living reward - point one I didn't
receive the +1 that doesn't happen until
I take the action exit from the square
and you think who cares about exactly
when it happened well we're gonna use
this running example enough and it's
gonna be in your project that it's good
to know exactly when it happens you
don't have off-by-one errors all the
time alright so here I go I'm gonna exit
boom and what happened here let's scroll
up I was in state three comma two
I took the action exit I ended in the
special state terminal State and I got
reward one so my total cumulative reward
was like 0.7 or something like that I'm
gonna do it again alright that was let's
make this a little more tense I'm going
the scary way
I'm gonna go east East I'm gonna go
north I'm gonna walk past the pit north
all right I'm going north anything could
happen
okay all right some years okay
some years this is really intense but
not this year alright so you get the
idea
but even though nothing spectacular
happened like falling into a fire pit
you did see a couple times where I
expected the most likely outcome would
be iMovies but I stayed put okay
as a result we can't have a plan which
is a sequence of actions because who
knows what's gonna happen when I take
those actions for EM DPS the analogous
concept to a plan is something called a
policy a policy isn't a sequence of
actions you take it is a function which
in a state tells you in action so it's
like a recommendation of an action
function okay policy you give it a state
it gives you an action back in general
when we want to when we say we solve an
MDP we're not just interested in any
policy or I'm just interested in the
optimal policy the optimal policy
policies are PI that little star
throughout these lectures and in general
in this class
can indicate optimality so we want
pi-star which is an optimal policy there
may be multiple equipment policies okay
a policy gives an action for each state
an optimal policy is one that maximizes
the expected utility if followed and an
explicit policy is a is an actual
explicit enumeration for each state of
where you should go and so for example
this map here that the robots looking at
for the grid world that is an explicit
policy it lists each state and what to
do that means following this policy is a
reflex agent you look up your state you
look up the action you do it no
computation is required all the
computation went into building this
policy in the first place
once you've got it you just do it
sometimes that's realistic sometimes
it's not so for example in something
like pac-man with dots the state space
may be so large you could never compute
or you know even write down the explicit
policy and so we would need different
methods we're going to talk about today
assumes that the MDP is small enough the
state space is small enough that we can
actually numerate the states and and
write down policies that's not always
going to be true
do you remember expect a max that didn't
actually compute policies either you
just executed it as a computation in
acetate it turned on the game tree for a
while and then it said take this action
so expect a max might be living inside a
function PI that computes the policy on
the fly on demand that's not what we're
going to talk about today but that is
another class of ways you can build
policies instead of being explicit
policies you could have an implicit
policy that requires computation each
time you try to access it alright let's
take a look at some optimal policies so
you can see the optimal policy right
here so there's the gem
there's the firepit and there's this
policy that says all right if you're
here at the start state you should go up
and around and to the gem okay
fair enough well it gets more
interesting isn't some of the other
squares so for example if you're in this
square here this policy says that you
should take the short way right you just
take the short way around and risk
the pit why why don't you go the long
way around well this is gonna be a
function of exactly how the living
reward which here is a penalty balances
against the risk you take by walking
past that pit and this is a general
example of we feed in the specification
of the model and the behavior emerges
through the computation okay so let's
look at some examples of different kinds
of behaviors all emerging from the same
computation of solving an MDP to get an
explicit policy for grid world so here's
an example there's still a plus 1 and a
minus 1 a good exit and bad exit and
remember each time step that you don't
exit you get a little reward in this
case it's negative so you get hit with a
tiny little tax - point 1 each time step
this is more of a toll than a tax and if
you look at this you can see that you
know as you'd expect if you're the start
state you might as well go the safe way
but if you're here even though you're
quite close to the shortcut it's still
going to send you around the long way
and that's because that living reward is
so minor that it's not worth the risk of
falling into the pit which is a
significant risk so you just pay the
extra price to go around you might like
slip a little bit as you go it might
take a little longer but you basically
go around the long way here's the really
interesting square right here what the
heck is that the living reward is very
small and that means this agent has a
lot of patience right it can afford to
take a lot of steps to get a large goal
to get a large reward later so it's
doing this odd thing where it's moving
into the wall what's up with that
so we fed all the rules into the agent
and what did it do it solved it and it
learned it basically learned an exploit
grid world has a bug and this agent
learned it
what is the bug if from this from this
from this this grid square here if you
go north you might fall into the pit if
you go south you might fall into the pit
if you go into the pit you're probably
gonna fall into the pit but if you head
towards the wall
there's no chance of falling into the
pit what's probably going to happen not
is probably going to happen you're
probably gonna end up where you are but
if you do it enough over and over and
over again eventually you'll sort of
slip to the left or the right and you
will have escaped to the danger square
without any risk of falling into the pit
okay this is you remember back you
remember the little I BOS playing soccer
we're like the way they shoot is they
like put their stomach on the ball and
then poop it out okay this is more or
less than a spontaneous discovery of a
behavior which is optimal but maybe not
what you would have predicted and it's a
consequence of the rules of the game all
right we can turn up the temperature
here and charge the agent more per step
so that taking your time is no longer
going to be as appealing and so in this
case you still you know go straight you
prefer the good goal to the bad goal but
here you're gonna you're you're gonna
risk falling in rather than taking ten
turns to shimmy your way out but you'll
still go the long way around if you're
in one of these squares let's turn up
the heat again here the reward is minus
0.4 think about that it's like starting
to be almost as big as the as the
rewards at the end of the game so now
this agent is not going to mess around
given the choice it would rather take
the safe way than the dangerous way but
if you're in this square you're just
gonna he's gonna run for it maybe you'll
fall into the pit but that's okay
because if you go the long way around
you're gonna accumulate so much negative
living or word that that doesn't make
sense what do you think's gonna happen
if I crank it all the way to negative 2
think about that for a second that fire
pit starts to look pretty good because
it's better than the reward you get
every step and so what are you gonna do
straight to the closest exit get me out
of this game ok all of these different
kinds of qualitative behaviors will
emerge from the same kind of computation
just as the differences in rewards and
the balances of those shift any
questions on that ok now we're gonna see
how to compute this stuff
that's Grid world it's really really
easy to think of search problems as
happening on a grid and by now you know
that many search problems have nothing
to do with a grid or any kind of spatial
structure I'm gonna give you another
example of an MDP that looks nothing
like grid world to give you a second
running example that we're gonna work a
lot with today and next time so this is
a super super simple example of a robot
car it's a very very simple example that
has only three states and what you see
here is a state transition diagram think
like a finite automaton that describes
the states and how they interact in this
MDP so we have a robot car it would like
to travel far and quickly and it's gonna
have three states obviously a huge
simplification there's going to be cool
warm and overheated and cool is the good
state the car would like to be cool warm
is okay but you start to risk
overheating and if you overheat the
game's over it's not actually directly
good or bad to be cool warmer overheated
because the rewards happen on the
transitions and in this case you've got
actions slow and fast and the way the
Trant the way the rewards happens on the
transitions is that you get twice as
many points for moving fast than for
moving slow regardless of where you land
the rewards can depend on where you land
like they did in grid world here they
don't they only depend in this case
actually on what state you're in and
what action you take so let's look and
see if we can just sort of wrap our
heads around this example so if you are
cool if the car is cool and you choose
slow you will get your plus-one reward
because you went slow and with
probability one you'll stay cool all
right what happens if you go fast well
if your car is cool and you go fast you
get the plus two for going fast
but what happens next is not
deterministic half the time you stay
cool and half the time you warm up if
you're warm and you go slow you get the
plus one reward for slow half the time
you stay warm but half the time you cool
down if you're warm and you go fast you
get a minus ten and you overheat and if
you overheat the game is over so what do
you do
what you do if it's cool go fast what
you if it's warm don't go fast
yeah go slow and well if you're
overheated you should you should reflect
back on the decisions that got you there
in this case you do not have to end up
there ever so there you go this is a
little MDP it's got a very small number
of states but you can imagine the games
can get very long because there's no
real end to this game unless you make a
mistake ok that's an example of another
MDP all right so let's think if we
wanted to figure out it's cool I just
asked you so if I want to know what to
do when the car is cool apparently you
can just ask the s 188 but if I wanted
to do that computationally how would I
figure out what the right action is
you've sort of already got a tool you've
got expectant max search but I can think
all right if I want to decide what to do
from the state cool I can think out the
possible futures just like we did with
games last week ok and if I think out
the possible futures I'll think well I
can go faster I can go slow that's gonna
be under my control but both are
possible and if I go slow only one
outcome can happen from my taking that
action and that is I end up back in the
state I started in if I go fast there
are two outcomes to that action I'll
either stay cool or I'll heat up I don't
know which will happen but I know they
both can happen and I know the
probabilities associated with them now
you might wonder what if I don't know
the probabilities I would say come back
next week for reinforcement learning
where we'll learn the probabilities for
now we know about them ok and then I can
just kind of keep extending this into
the future and I can see this tree which
will look exactly like an expectant max
tree there will be an alternation
between actions that I can choose
amongst and then chance nodes which
describe the possible outcomes which I
know a distribution over but I can't
force an outcome it's not gonna be as
bad as worst-case there's just a
distribution ok so here's a search tree
that describes that one thing should
already strike you about this search
tree anybody notice anything that didn't
really happen and expect a max
one thing is it's the same three states
over and over and over and over again so
doing some exponential amount of
computation over these three states just
like can't be the right thing right
these same sub trees appear this tree
here is exactly the same as this one
here so we're gonna want to be careful
of that in general whenever you have a
Markov decision problem you can think
about there being a tree like this
projected from each state so from each
state there is a tree of futures that
has that state at the root and then the
actions available to you
branching out when we talk about s s is
a state ok the actions are a those are
the actions available to you and we've
had those for a while now here's where
we get to something that's new and a
little bit counterintuitive but super
useful
what are these chance nodes from expect
to max what do they represent well s is
a state of the world and a is an action
you choose and then after you choose an
action it's going to resolve to some
state s prime and there's going to be
multiple possible outcomes which are
governed by a probability distribution
but what about this node right here I
was in a state there could have been
other states I was in that state I chose
an action it may or may not have been a
smart action but I've chosen it but I
don't yet know what happened as a result
being in this situation where you're in
a state and you've committed to an
action but it has not resolved is called
a Q State okay and it represents it
represents having chosen an action but
not seen its resolution this whole
sequence here this little tree si s
prime is called a transition and on this
arc right here when your Q state si
resolves to a particular result s prime
that's a transition it's labeled with a
probability from your MD P as well as a
reward and here that reward is shown as
a gem but the reward can be negative for
example both the the firepit and the
cliff so the both the firepit in the
living reward were both negative okay so
this little search tree this is MDPs in
a slide as the search
everything we do every algorithm every
quantity it all comes back to this
search tree where you have a state a
sequence of actions that you maximize
over and for each action a sequence of
outcomes which you have a probability
distribution over okay we'll talk about
solution in a bit let's take a step back
and try to figure out how an agent
should think about a sequence of
utilities because another thing that
happens in an MDP is that you saw when
we are in grid world those rewards would
sort of be trickled in step by step so
we need to be able to think about our
preferences over these sequences so what
preferences should an agent have over a
sequence of rewards first should an
agent like more rewards or less rewards
so for example if I give an agent a
choice between a sequence of three
rewards one two and two or three rewards
two three and four which one should I
pick well I mean I guess I have to like
define whether positive is good or not
in this case we've been talking about
them as rewards so it seems pretty
reasonable that the agent should prefer
to get more rewards rather than less
okay great
if that's all I wanted to accomplish I
would just add up the rewards and I
would say hey agent go find the go act
in such a way as to maximize the sum of
rewards there's one other thing that
turns out to be really important in MVPs
and that has to do with a choice between
now or later so for example here's two
sequences of rewards one is zero Awards
followed by zero / reward followed by a
reward of one or another sequence where
it's a reward of one followed by zero
followed by zero same sum of rewards
what should the agent prefer the reward
now or the reward later or should it be
indifferent how many people say a reward
now give me rewards how many people want
the reward later how many people are
indifferent okay so it is totally
reasonable to be indifferent right
sometimes sometimes that's an
appropriate formulation but in most
cases and most people raise their hand
for rewards now in most cases it is also
reasonable to per for rewards sooner
okay and so how are we going to handle
that adding up the rewards doesn't
actually capture the fact that rewards
soon
are more useful than rewards later for
example if somebody comes up to you and
says hey would you like $100 now or in
20 years will you be indifferent what if
they say and of course that's totally
it's easy to see that you might say well
I'd rather that reward now but what if
they say would you like $100 now or 110
dollars in 20 years you probably still
want the reward now and so that means
there's going to be an implicit
trade-off between having things soon and
having things be big so it's reasonable
to maximize the sum of your rewards in
fact that's what we've been doing so far
with grid world it's also reasonable to
prefer were rewards now to rewards later
one solution to capturing these
different reasonable utility functions
is to say that the values of rewards are
going to decay in an exponential way so
for example here's a reward and if you
get it now it might actually be worth 1
right now but if you think about that
reward that same reward being in the
future it could be worth the same then
you would just be summing rewards or we
can penalize it a way that's very
convenient formally and mathematically
to penalize things is to say that in the
next time step it won't be worth 1
anymore it'll be worth less it will be
discounted it will be worth some amount
gamma which we can pick gamma has to be
greater than zero to make sense and it
has to be less than or equal to 1 if you
want the things to be worth less later
but there are different points you could
set in between and then in two time
steps it would be worth gamma squared
and so the value of a reward will decay
exponentially or the rate of that decay
is is something that is actually an
input to the problem rather than
something you can derive okay so in two
questions
one is how do we discount and the second
is why do we discount so how we discount
is actually the easier of those
questions so remember if we think about
there being this tree of possible
futures where every time you take an
action sort of the world responds with
telling you how that action what the
outcome was so here you were asked you
took action a you landed in s Prime and
at
that point there's this little call-out
which is hey I took s I was it asked I
took action AI landed in s prime so here
you go you can have your reward R of si
s Prime and then you get another award
here you get another reward and another
reward here and what you can do is
conceptually you want each of those
rewards to get hit with an extra factor
of gamma and say if you were running an
expectant Max search you could just set
it up so that each time you recurse to
the next level of a tree and you
returned a result you hit it with a
factor of gamma so that each level down
picks up an extra factor of gamma this
has some really interesting properties
like things way way in the future
eventually just don't matter very much
because they've been hit with so many
factors of gamma that they're just not
worth very much to your computation so
why should we discount one is that
sooner rewards probably really do have
higher utility than later Awards and
sometimes this sort of like has to do
with the mechanics of of the problem
itself like maybe this is money and you
can invest it or something like that and
there is actually a story where this is
the mechanism is something exponential
or something decaying in value but it
also helps our algorithms converge and
there's another reason why why these are
very convenient which I'll talk about in
a second okay so that's discounting in
general and MDPs we say either we sum
the rewards or we sum them up with a
discount that hitch each time step so
that things farther onto the future are
worth eventually lost if you think about
it these are actually the exact same
thing because we've used that gamma
equal to one you'll end up with the
undiscounted case okay so if you think
about a discount of 0.5 that sequence
one two three is not worth one plus two
plus three so one two and three are the
rewards the utility of the sequence
could be the sum of the rewards or it
could be the sum of the discounted
rewards which is in general what we'll
do and here that means it's 1 times 1
because it hasn't discounted yet plus 2
at the second time step but it gets hit
with a discount in this case point 5 and
then on the third time step you get a 3
but it's been hit with that discount
twice so it'll only worth a quarter of
what it would have been worth of the
current time step and so the sum here
isn't six it's much less and that 3 even
though it's the largest number is
actually worth less than the one at the
next time stuff okay so if you look at
this among other things this means that
one two three is not as good in utility
as three two one
so when we specify an MDP we have to
specify a discount which tells us how to
turn the sequence of rewards into an
utility over the sequence it's either
going to be the sum or the discounted
sum all right
remember when we when we talked about
utilities and we talked about there
being even before you have utilities
which is going around and assigning
numbers to outcomes we talked about
something more primitive which is
preferences I like two scoops of ice
cream more than one scoop of ice cream
and then I can go around saying how many
you tiles each scoop is or something
like that we talked about there being a
set of rational preferences these are
preferences that seemed like any
reasonable set of utility should respect
them and then we could derive things
like if your preferences obey these
rational constraints then they can be
formulated in a certain way as a utility
function there's an equivalent notion
here for sequences and it it's a notion
of stationary preferences so there's a
theorem that says let's imagine that
your preferences are stationary that
means if you prefer the sequence of
rewards a a 1 a 2 a 3 a 4 and so on to
this other sequence B B 1 B 2 B 3 so you
like the a sequence better than the B
sequence great who cares why you like a
better than B if I tell you hey how
about for the first time step I'll give
you the same reward R and then I'm gonna
give you a and B well if you liked a
better than B now and your preferences
are stationary
it means you will also like a better
than B shifted one time step if that
first time step has the same reward it
seems like reasonable it's reasonable to
assume that preferences are stationary
if preferences are stationary it turns
out there are only two ways to define
utilities which as we talked about are
basically the same thing which is you
either some that you do either some the
instantaneous rewards at each time step
or you something with a discount and you
think huh that's a little weird
maybe my preferences aren't stationary
and sometimes they're not because for
example if you are playing a game
like save life where you don't have an
infinite number of time steps it could
be that by pushing the rewards out
something just comes too late
something falls off the edge or
something like that and so when things
have finite horizons sometimes things
get things get trickier and have to be
handled in different ways alright let's
do a quick quiz first any questions
before you quiz the quiz is gone
any questions yep
it's a great question the question is
why are we doing exponential rather than
subtractive discounts so let me separate
two things very important there's two
things going on in a grid world not an
MDP in general a grid world robots
north-south east-west and so on there is
a living reward which might be a penalty
at each time that is that is an R that's
a reward that has nothing to do with a
discount then there's a discount which
so far we've been talking about the grid
worlds as having a discount of a1 they
were undiscounted so far so you can
always penalize at each time step as
part of the reward structure but
mathematically when you talk about
sequences being converted into a single
number that's when we use the
exponential formulation and the reason
we do that is one it's mathematically
very convenient
it helps us prove that things converge
it reflects a lot of real-world things
lots of in many cases by pushing
something out in time for example
interest and so on on money things
really are exponential and then beyond
that there's also this theorem about
stationary preferences which only holds
for the exponential case and not for the
additive case but it's a great question
and sometimes we do actually like in
grid world want to have something
additive going on where every time step
costs the same now we can do that too ok
yep
I'm sorry could you ask it again
so the question is how can I know the
sequence of rewards when the future is
undetermined and before you act you
don't know what sequence rewards you
will get but what these algorithms do is
they plan I could take this action I
could take that action and based on the
Akridge of actions I take in the actions
I might then take later I have to sort
of hedge with all of those possible
outcomes and probabilities in the
appropriate way so we need to be able to
compute okay if I had this reward or I
had this reward how would I how would I
combine them and how would I think about
them but it's true you don't actually
know which future you're gonna get until
you actually play the game so solving an
MDP happens offline you don't actually
play it you consider the probabilities
and you make your policy you can then go
actually execute the policy and then
you're going to get one particular
experience and that's going to be
analogous to what we do in reinforcement
learning where we just play the game and
something happens and the next time we
play it something else might happen and
then we'll be in a position of having to
learn right now we know the rules of the
game and so even without actually
playing it we can solve in a way that
hedges all of those various
probabilities appropriately okay great
questions okay let's do a quiz quiz on
discounting so this is a grid world you
can go east-west and exit you can only
exit at an e it's deterministic so that
if you go east you'll actually go east
and if you exit a day you get 10 if you
exit a year you get 1 if gamma is 1 what
is the optimal policy so what should I
do
say at B here I should go this way all
right now it starts to get tricky what
should I do in the center I should go
left all right now if gamma is 1 what
should I do over here at D I should go
left because what will I sequence of
rewards will I get I'll get zero zero
zero okay and then at the end it's been
pushed farther out I'll eventually get
that ten but that's fine because I'm not
actually discounting it however if gamma
is one I'll give you the easy one I
should go here I'll give you another
easy one in the center it's gonna be the
same amount of time either way but
here's the interesting case
what happens here if it's 0.1 well if I
go this way what am I gonna get I'm not
gonna get one because it's gonna be
pushed out as time staff if I go this
way I'll get 0.1 what if I go this way
I'm pushed out 1 2 3 time steps so I'm
gonna get point 0 0 1 and that means
it's better to just go right because I'd
rather get that one by the time I get to
the 10 it'll be so decayed I don't even
want it so in this case sooner is more
important than more and that trade-off
is encapsulated in gamma which among
other things specifies in a soft way
what's often informally called the
horizon of the agent how far out I'm
thinking now in an MDP you're always
thinking all the way out but in a way
that tails off and the faster that
discount tails off the more greedy
you're gonna be the more you'll pursue
rewards sooner rather than larger
rewards later okay I think we'll just go
from there a couple more things and
we'll take a break and talk about
algorithms for solving these MVPs all
right so let's say you're that racecar
and you can go fast or you can go slow
and if you play your cards right you're
never gonna actually overheat so the
game will last forever and go fast fast
slow slow fast fast fast and what's your
total we're gonna be infinite if you go
slow all the time what's it gonna be
infinite if you go fast when you can and
then slow when you have to infinite and
so that's not good I mean it's good if
you like rewards because they're
infinite but it's a problem for
algorithms that are going to be trying
to decide between different actions if
all the quantities were deciding between
are just infinity so how do we handle
the possibility the games could go on
forever or and make our algorithms
difficult well there's basically three
solutions and sometimes they're
appropriate and sometimes they're not
one solution is to talk about finite
horizon right in this case we terminate
all our episodes after say something
like T steps life is an example of this
we don't know what T is but it's not
infinity and so in this case you say
okay car you've got a hundred moves go
do your
okay having a finite horizon can give
rise to non-stationary policies where
the policy the optimal action depends on
the time left first thought that might
be weird why can the state you're in
some state why does what you should do
depend on how much time is left and the
answer is you've seen this in legging
every sports game you've ever seen it's
like some crazy stuff happens at the end
right before the timer runs out with
these cars you might like risk
overheating at the last second because
who cares the the game's gonna end
anyway and so as especially as you get
close to the end of a finite horizon
game sometimes the policies can change
greatly but that's one way to make
things finite you just declare the end
okay another way to just use discounting
a nice thing about discounting is even
though the sequences of rewards can be
infinite and their sums can be infinite
they're discounted sums usually are not
so if gamma is between 0 & 1 and the
rewards themselves are bounded the sum
through some infinite series magic is
going to be bounded okay and then the
last thing is some games have what's
called an absorbing state which is that
you look at and you say okay I can
actually see that the games can go on
forever but with probability 1 it's
gonna stop so the probability that you
keep looking out and not having the game
end tails off to zero that's good enough
in many cases ok all right we're gonna
recap we're gonna break and then I'm
gonna give you some algorithms ok so to
recap Markov decision processes they're
like non-deterministic search problems
they've got a set of states just like
search including a start state they have
a set of actions just like search except
now instead of the action taking you
from an s 2 and s prime it can take you
to multiple s Prime's so we have a
transition function which tells you for
each s prime how likely it is possibly
zero if it's not going to happen
and for each transition si s prime
there's a reward that tells you how many
points you get on that transition right
then and then a discount which tells you
how to add up a sequence in the
appropriate way by multiplying in a
discount each time the quantities that
we've talked about so far we've talked
about policies which is a mapping of
States to actions and utilities which is
a sum of discounted rewards across the
entire game of the MDP ok
I'm gonna take a quick break and then
we're going to talk about how to solve
them which will lead into reinforcement
learning after next lecture okay
two-minute break quick break and then
we'll start again
okay all right I don't know if that was
actually two minutes it felt like two
minutes there's about two minutes all
right we're gonna talk about solving
MVPs how do you solve an MVP the way you
solve an MVP the input this is really
important because in reinforcement
learning it's gonna look so similar and
it's gonna be so different the input to
the input when you solve an MVP is an
MDP that means somebody tells you hey
here are the states here the actions
here are the transition probabilities
here are the rewards and then your
output is a policy it is a mapping from
each state to the optimal action okay in
order to do that we need to define a
whole bunch of quantities that are gonna
be useful in this computation they're
actually going to vary peril they're
gonna be very parallel to things that
you computed with expect a max search
we're gonna have to define them and then
we're gonna have to mathematically state
how they relate to each other which will
then turn into algorithms for computing
them okay so here are some important
quantities associated with an MDP we'll
show this for grid world first okay the
first is the value of a state and this
is going to turn out to be both the
utility of being in that state and
acting optimally and it's also going to
correspond to what expect to max would
have produced so values the written v
there's a value for each state v is a
value v star is the optimal value that
means the value you will achieve on
average because it can be an expected
value on average if you act optimally
starting from state s okay
some states will have higher values than
others because some states are better to
be in than others right and much better
to be right next to the goal then in
some right and next to the fire pit
remember there are also Q States s is a
state it corresponds to a max node and
expect a max and it has a value that
value is what you would do if you sort
of acted optimally from that point a Q
state corresponds to a chance node in
the same sense that there are good
states and bad states and you just have
to compute the value of each particular
state like you're in this state you
could wish you were in another state but
this state has whatever value it has Q
states have values you're in the state
and you're performing this action the
value of that Q state is the expected
utility of starting
out having taken action a from state s
and acting oftenly thereafter in the
same way that there are some states that
are good in some states that are bad
there are some few states that are good
in there some few states that are bad
their values have to do with what will
happen if from that state and q state
you act optimally in the future there's
then an optimal policy pi is a policy pi
star is an optimal policy pi star of s
is the action recommended by this
optimal policy from state s and it'll be
something like in the state go north
okay so let's take a look at these in
grid world all right so here's grid
world this is a particular setting to
know these particular values you need to
know what was the noise probability what
was the living reward what was the
discount and so on but qualitatively
here you can see that if you are in this
state your value is 1 because you only
have one possible future you take exit
you exit you get plus 1 if you're in the
pit the value is negative 1
you only have one future exit minus 1
everywhere else these values represent
optimal play from that point and then
all the possible outcomes have various
probabilities this is an average as an
expectation well I'll figure out how to
compute that expectation but from here
this means that on average sometimes
you'll accidentally slip and fall into
the you know from this this 8 point 8 5
includes both going straight into the
good exit and exiting it also includes
slipping here trying to get back but
slipping again and then you know falling
into the fire and so on and these arrows
you can see the numbers are the sum of
discounted rewards including the living
reward and the final reward under the
optimal policy the optimal policy is
shown by the arrows okay so those are
the values of the states and so you look
this state's really good because you're
just gonna get a good reward this states
pretty good because unless you get
really unlucky you're gonna get a good
reward pretty soon this state down here
in the lower left the one we had
sometimes been calling the start state
its values only about 0.5 why well sort
of by the time you make your way up some
combination of living reward and
probability of falling into the pit and
just
counts have whittled away that plus one
and averaged in a whole bunch of other
possible outcomes and so you're out your
state states value is lower it is better
to be in this state than this state but
the whole point of computing these
values is not to notice that this is a
bad state
but rather to figure out what is the
optimal thing to do if you're there okay
so those are values every state has a
number and the farther you are from the
goal in grid world in general the worse
your value is going to be what is that
these are the Q values so each square is
a state and in each square there are
four actions north south east and west
so each of these little pie slices
represents that that action the top pie
slice is the North action and so for
example you can see that that point
eight five from the state up here
corresponds to taking the action east so
the value of the Q state three comma
three action east is point eight five
there are other Q values for that state
in the same way that states can be good
states or bad States and you'd rather if
you can control it be in the good States
there's good actions and bad actions and
if you can control it you'd rather take
the good actions and so if you go south
here you're gonna end up in a worse
State and then even if you act optimally
thereafter you're not gonna get that
same point eight five and so you can see
the Q value here is lower than it is for
the other actions branching out of that
state okay and it just had a little
episode okay so those are the values the
fundamental operation in solving mdps is
to compute the value and here we mean
expect a max or expected value of a
state so we need to know the expected
utility under optimum actions and that's
going to be an average sum of discounted
rewards expect a max computed that but
right now we're gonna try to find
another algorithm and in order to do
that we're gonna write down recursively
some properties that hold between these
values that will let us formulate an
algorithm so let's write this in blue
the value of a state so let's talk about
the optimal value of some state s oops
we're always going to think about this
little expected max future how good is
it to be at some state s well I don't
know but I can relate it to some
quantities I can relate it to how good
other states and q states are so in
particular I could write down that the
value of being in state s is just the
maximum over all of the actions I can
take from that state of the Q value the
optimum Q value of s comma a that just
says that the expect a max value of this
max node is the max over these of the Q
values of those q States all right well
that doesn't really help because I don't
know Q star either so what is the value
or you can think about is what would I
get if I ran expect to max from this
chance node s comma a well I can write
that down too so I can go change colors
for chance note here the expected max
value of being in state s and having
chosen a regardless of whether a was in
fact a good action you have to compute
this for all of them well I don't know
why I got into State Aston I don't know
why I took it upon myself to choose a
but I do know what's gonna happen next
right the average the average outcome
I'm gonna get is always gonna break down
into I'm gonna get a reward from state s
from action a that reward is gonna
depend on the s prime I land in okay so
I got a reward for the transition who
knows which s prime it is but I'm gonna
get a reward and then when I land in s
prime that's down here I'm going to then
act optimally right so what is that the
OP at optimal action from state s prime
is gonna give me a score of V star s
prime in the future so my score from s
comma a is the instantaneous reward our
of si s prime plus the future often will
reward V star of s prime two more things
one that future is discounted so I stick
a gamma there the second thing is I
don't know which s prime is going to
happen right I'm taking a but I don't
know what outcome s prime I'm gonna get
I have to average over them the way I
average over them is I have to take an
average i sum them all up weighted by
the transition probabilities t of si s
Prime and this thing here
is the probability of s prime given s
comma a okay so here's sort of a a
system of equations here's a system of
equations people often in line these
things so you will usually see these
things in lined when you see them in
lined it says what is the expect of ax
value of a state well it is the
instantaneous reward that you will get
in the next time step plus the future
reward from the successor state the
future is discounted I have to average
over all of the possible consequences of
my action so I have to sum over the S
Prime's I have to wait take the weighted
sum of them and then of course a is
under my control so I take which ever
action is best this defines a system of
equations that relate V Star of States
to V stars of other states and you look
at that and you say that how does that
help me because now I've written
something I don't know in terms of
something else I don't know okay
moreover because of that max this is not
a linear system of equations so you
can't just invert some matrix or
something like that so we're gonna talk
about how to solve these equations but
this is the core system of equations
these are called the bellman equations
these are the core recursive definitions
of values and Q values of states these
are really really good things to stare
at until you are totally totally sure
you get what they're saying because you
will see variations of these over and
over and over again so you can stare at
them I'm going to erase them and replace
them with beautiful latex so you can see
on your slides okay because no one
should have to read my handwriting all
right
so that was a recursive definition of
these values in terms of other optimal
quantities I can define the optimal
value at a state let's make a erase that
I can define the optimal value of a
state in terms of the optimal values of
Q States I can define the optimal value
of Q States in terms of the optimal
values of states using these look-ahead
equations that relate values of states
to values of states one step
in time and again these are called
one-step look-ahead equations or bellman
equations okay let's look at that Racing
search tree again
so if we look at this well I could run
expect a max on this but when I look at
this I think maybe there's a better
algorithm because those same states seem
to appear over and over again and as we
know their optimal values are all
interrelated by the system of equations
okay so here's the racing this is the
search tree to depth one if I continued
it forward right that tree is gonna grow
it's gonna grow rapidly it's gonna grow
exponentially fast and if you look at
that you think it can't possibly be
right to run expect the max over this
whole giant tree that's growing
exponentially fast but in fact only has
three states occurring over and over
again it's a tiny little system of
equations there should be a way to more
efficiently just directly connect all
these quantities and compute them and
that's what we're gonna talk about now
is an algorithm for this so why should
we not just run expect a max well
problem one we're doing way too much
work right among other things this whole
subtree is exactly the same as this
whole subtree so there's at a minimum at
a minimum there's there's duplicated
work and in fact there's exponentially
duplicated work that's one problem
second and so that's the state's
repeated problem a second this tree is
actually infinite so running expect to
max on an infinite tree is sort of a bad
idea and can you fix these problems
right now if I stop this lecture you
could fix all these problems you could
say all right we'll look well why don't
we cache this stuff once I compute
something why don't I cache that okay
and actually instead of doing an
infinite tree didn't we talk about how
things deep in the tree if they're
discounted don't matter
I'll just truncate this at depth 100
well actually if you put these ideas
together you will have more or less
reinvented the algorithm we're going to
talk about now which is an algorithm
told called value iteration but the
algorithm we have works the other
direction rather than starting at the
top doing things recursively caching as
we go and trying to depth limit as we go
the algorithm we're gonna have is going
to start at the bottom and work our way
upward until we decide that the tree is
deep enough okay
all right the key idea we're gonna need
in order for us to have this algorithm
value iteration is an idea of time
limited values and so what we're gonna
do is we're the star so V star was a
very tricky quantity it is the value of
being in a state and acting optimally
that's very tricky right because that
could go on forever it could be an
infinite depth thing we're gonna define
something much more tractable which is V
sub K of a state V sub K is the optimal
value of start if you start in that
state and play optimally it's the
expected value of starting in that state
and playing optimally if the game is
going to end in K more time steps why is
this useful this is really useful right
now suddenly that tree is no longer
infinite and this quantity is exactly
what a depth K expect to max would give
if you started at s so we already have
an algorithm and in fact if we save or
do if we save repeated work we'll have
an even better algorithm in a second
okay so we take a look at this tree and
and we say well looking at this there's
a computation from say state blue of
what can happen in two time steps this
is that tree and if we were unexpected
max over that it will compute the
average rewards I will get if I act
optimally I do the right thing at all
the max nodes and the game ends after
two so I can just think of this little
tree as v2 that the root is of depth two
and it has some value and if I see this
tree occur a hundred times I can just
keep plugging that value in and it
represents the value of being in state
blue which was cool and acting optimally
for two time steps so let's take a look
about how this looks in grid world
all right so here is our favorite
example of a the grid with a good and a
bad exit v-0 is very important to
understand and it's also very simple if
I have zero time steps what's a time
step it's a reward zero means zero more
rewards what value will I get under
optimal play from the good exit zero
okay no time to get a reward bad exit
zero lower left corner zero everything
zero because there are zero more rewards
so my future score from that state is
zero okay easy but not helpful but now I
can ask what about after one if I if I
if I allow myself one more reward before
I end the game well some of these states
will no longer have zero optimal value
like the upper right what can I do in
one time step well there's only one
thing I can do in one time step which is
call exit and I get plus 1 how about the
fire pit what can I do in one time step
there's only one choice according to the
rules of the game take eggs I can get
minus 1 anywhere else
what can I do in one time step I can
move and get the living reward if the
living reward is zero these are the
values for one time step so this is V
sub 1 these are the values achievable
under optimal play on average for one
more time step now what if I had two
time steps think about it some of these
places like the lower left there's just
nowhere you can get in two time steps
that's going to give you any reward
other than zero presuming the living
reward is zero but here's V sub two
there's two interesting things that
happened one the upper right square here
became point seven two why what does
that represent well what can happen in
two time steps
I can move east succeed and take the
exit and get plus one that has a certain
probability I can also move east fail
slip go in the wrong direction try to
move back and run out of time that's
going to have value zero and so that
point seven two represents a mixture of
things where I didn't quite make it to
an exit and the one case where I just
barely made it into the exit in time and
that has when you average all it
together you get 0.72 the more
interesting one is the zero right below
it the
one right next to the fire pit why is
that zero because I can exit the game in
two time steps I could jump into the pit
and get a minus one but that's not
optimal play so under optimal play I
will I will avoid that I will go I will
you know I will take some other sequence
of actions which does not include that
and I can basically guarantee myself an
average of zero right I can make sure I
don't actually fall in and then as I
look farther into the future four five
six you can see that eventually I'm
looking far enough into the future that
even from the lower left I can start to
see ways of eventually getting to a good
reward now I can't see all of them
because some of the ways of getting to
that good reward are gonna take more
than six or more than seven or more than
eight time steps because they involve
slipping or some other thing that's
gonna slow me down but as I do this and
I sort of push this out eventually this
will stop and looking farther and
farther into the future eventually will
not contribute much if there's a
discount I want to show you one more
thing on this I'll show that same thing
again I want you to watch not the values
because they're just gonna kind of like
the green will sort of bleed outward I
want you to watch the arrows so first
they change a lot but once I get to here
watch the arrows the numbers are still
fine-tuning but after a certain point
the arrows are done flipping and this is
a common thing that as I look deeper and
deeper I can I've just like I have these
residual rewards that I can start to
that I can keep accumulating forever I'm
late so it's like computing the limit of
a series right I keep kind of
accumulating but the actual policies
implied by that depth of search will
eventually stabilize and that often
happens long before the values
themselves do okay so this actually
gives us all we need to define the core
algorithm here which will define now and
then we will extend and pick up next
time okay and that is
I look at this tree of all the possible
futures in ways this game can play out
which includes these same repeating
units over and over again and I look at
the bottom and I say what are what's
down there what are these little expect
to max fragments well they're all depth
zero trees they don't have any rewards
in them so I know I can summarize this
exponentially large number of leaves
with just the terminal values v-0 which
we know are all zero and then if I look
above that there are a bunch of repeated
sub trees these are the v1 trees over
and over and over and over again okay so
I can summarize that whole stripe across
this tree by just the values of each
state that I could then reuse and reuse
and reuse and if I go up v2 v3 and now
at the top there's not actually that
much tree but that value at the top is
v4 if I consider this tree to truncate
after four more rewards okay so this is
basically how this algorithm is going to
flow I'm going to start with v-0 which I
know to be zero and I'm going to go
through and I'm going to compute a new
vector of values each path through this
I will be computing a vector which
correspond to depth limited expect a max
computations and each time this vector
gets each new vector that gets produced
for k plus 1 will represent having done
expect a max in a larger and larger tree
without having to have done it
explicitly eventually these vectors will
stop changing very much and this process
will terminate okay so value iteration
is the algorithm it's basically like
building a big layer cake where first I
decide what could I accomplish in zero
time steps okay if I know that what can
I accomplish in one if I know that what
can I accomplish in two and I stop
whenever it appears to have converged
all right so here's value iteration the
algorithm we're going to go through this
now and we will extend and improve this
next time in value iteration you start
with V 0 that is for each state you
compute your average rewards under
optimal play for 0 more time steps so
it's just a vector of zeros then
you imagine you are given a vector of VK
for each state this only works when the
number of states is manageable and can
be enumerated okay and so for each you
have VK you know what happens if you
would if you compute K time step search
from each state and now using that as a
building block we're going to compute a
VK plus 1 value for each and that means
the value the average rewards under
optimal play for k plus one more time
steps and that's just the same little
expectant max tree fragment we say well
if I want to know what I can achieve on
average in K plus 1 steps from s I'm
gonna say well what am I gonna do well
I'm gonna max over the actions available
to me right I'm gonna state I can choose
an action when that happens I'm gonna be
in a queue state si but I need to know
what s prime is gonna happen before I
can compute rewards I don't know which s
prime is gonna happen
but I know a distribution over them so I
can take an average so I sum over all of
them I weight each option S prime by its
probability and now for each outcome S
Prime I'm gonna get an instantaneous
reward R of S is prime and then well
I'll have K time steps left
how much score will I accumulate over
that K time step well it depends where I
land I landed in s and then I'm gonna
play optimally but with fewer time steps
so it's gonna be V sub K because that's
all the time that's left for state s
prime where I landed and I can stick my
my discount in there this looks exactly
like the bellman equations that related
optimal values to other optimal values
except that wasn't an algorithm this is
an algorithm it relates VK plus 1 to VK
but I know VK if I have a vector V K's I
can then visit each state compute its VK
plus 1 with a one step look ahead like a
one ply expect a max search using this
update so how expensive is this well I
have to visit each s so I get a factor
of s and then for each S I'm gonna do a
little expect to max so I'm gonna get a
factor of a as I consider each action
and then for each action I need khun's
consider every possible state that
results in the
worst-case every state can result in
every other state so I'll get another
factor of s in practice you don't
usually get that second factor of s
because actions have a limited amount of
possible successors s Prime okay but
there's your your complexity is that
good it really really depends on how
many states you have so for now we're
going to imagine our sets of states is
small which is exactly the opposite of
what we did when we had search we
imagined our set of states was so huge
you could never enumerate it well we
will fix the distance between these two
things when we get to state a state
function approximation about a week from
today okay so this thing will converge
towards optimal values but I'll prove
that next time
so let's should we do an example now you
guys are all like closing your books so
who wants an example let's do it
Democratic Lee who wants to just be free
all right all right it sounds like we're
gonna do a quick example all right b0
what's v-0 from each state remember the
CarMD P it's zero because in zero time
steps you can get zero rewards all right
v1 you don't even need to know they
algorithm you can just think what will I
accomplish on average if I play for one
more time step what if I'm overheated
zero no more rewards for you you're
overheated reflect on your life choices
all right what if you're in the cool
state yours only one time left go for it
go fast you're gonna get to some times
all the time who knows what state you'll
end up in but you always get the same
reward yep excellent question if you are
in the state overheated know you don't
get a minus 10 you get a minus 10 as you
transition into that state in that state
you can imagine there's like a little
low that's unexpected okay you can
imagine there's a little loop here that
says zero yeah no that's a great
question okay so if you're uncool you
get to if you are in the red warm state
what can you accomplish in one time time
step well you've only got two choices
your
gonna go faster you're gonna go slow and
then you can compute well if I went fast
I would be guaranteed a minus 10 if I
went slow I would be guaranteed a 1 that
sounds better and so that represents
optimal play the other one doesn't hurt
you because you're not gonna do it okay
here's where things get interesting from
overheated you still have zero you you
the game is over at that point um so
let's say you are in the cool state and
you think okay I've got two time steps
left I could try to enumerate all of the
lengths to futures right there's some
number of them I could try to enumerate
them all but that's not what this
algorithm does this algorithm says what
am I gonna do well I'm in this cool
state so I'm it cool and I've got two
choices I can go slow or I can go fast
what happens if from cool I go slow
well from cool I go slow if I go slow I
will receive one in the next time step I
will be guaranteed to land it cool and
then I will do the optimal thing v1 I
don't have to think about it once I only
have one time step left I've got a cache
right here
lower on the slide and so what's that
I'll get to in the next time step or I
could go fast if I go fast what's gonna
happen well remember I'm in cool right
now when I go fast I am going to get two
points for going fast but what happens
next depends on whether or not I heat up
if I heat up which happens half the time
I will land in warm and thereafter
receive one if I don't eat up our land
in cool and thereafter receive two
looking at my cache and so I'm either
gonna get two plus two or I'm gonna get
two plus one both equally likely and
therefore on average my score here will
be three point five under optimal play
okay I don't have to worry about what
happens if I go slow because I'm not
going to do that I can control that but
I do need to worry that when I go fast
I might heat up or I might not and
that's going to recurse into what I've
already come
and then if you look at this this value
here you'll see you'll undergo the same
computation you look at and you say well
I'm either gonna go fast or I'm gonna go
slow and in each case you do the next
ply of the expect to max it grounds out
in v1 that you've already computed and
you can try it on your own you'll get
2.5 okay now if I keep doing this what
are they going to converge to they will
not converge this is a without a
discount this is one of these defective
cases where your your rewards will go
infinite we'll talk about what that
means next time so these the answers are
on the slide next time I'll talk about
why this converges and we'll talk about
another class of algorithms all right
thanks everyone